Merlin D. Bishop Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Merlin D. Bishop Papers.
undated, 1924-1975.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bishop, Merlin D.
7.5 linear feet.
Merlin D. Bishop was born 5 October 1907, in Alhambra, Illinois. Bishop worked at the Ford Motor Company between 1925 and 1931. He then attended Wayne University (Detroit, MI) and in 1935-1936, was a member of the Extension Staff of Brookwood Labor College. He was later involved with the United Auto Workers of America, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America and the Connecticut Governor's Fact-Finding Commission on Education.
MSS19970024
Biography
Merlin D. Bishop was born 5 October 1907, in Alhambra, Illinois to William F. and Lena Bishop. He married Dorothy Hubbard in December 1936 and had one daughter, Martha W. Bishop.
Bishop worked at the Ford Motor Company between 1925 and 1931. He then attended Wayne University (Detroit, MI) and in 1935-1936, was a member of the Extension Staff of Brookwood Labor College. Following Brookwood, he joined the teaching staff of the Federal Emergency Relief Administration as assistant state supervisor of the worker education program. In 1936, he was appointed temporary education director of the United Automobile workers (UAW) and became full-time director in 1937-1938. He was the educational director of the Philadelphia joint board of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (1939-1943). In 1943 he was the international representative, sub-regional director, of the International Union, UAW, and held that position in Hartford as of 1947. In 1970, Bishop became the sub-regional director of the UAW. In his career he also wrote several labor education leaflets, pamphlets and instruction guides.
Bishop was also active in higher education in Connecticut, serving on the Governor's Fact-Finding Commission on Education from 1948 to 1951. In 1950, he was appointed to the Board of Trustees of the University of Connecticut and served as secretary of the Board from 1963 until 1972. He was also on the Governor's Library Study Commission (1961-1962), the Governor's Higher Education Study Commission (1963-1964), and the Labor Education Center Study Committee (Bishop Committee) (1964-1967).
Scope and Content
The Bishop papers contain publications, correspondence, reports and notes relevant to labor and labor education, Young Women's Christian Association, United Auto Workers and multiple University and State commissions. Unusual items include information on teaching methods, labor songs, drama and literature; background on the planning and construction of the UConn Health Center, minutes of the University's Board of Trustees and, household employment, women workers and course notes.
Arrangement
Series I: Labor Union Materials ( 1936-1972 ) consists of papers and published materials relating to labor unions and labor education.
Series II: University of Connecticut ( 1950-1975 ) is divided further into three subseries A: Board of Trustees, B: Connecticut Commission on Higher Education and, C: Governor's Fact-Finding Commission on Education.
Series III: Dorothy H. Bishop ( 1924-1947 ) includes the papers of Dorothy Bishop and her activities in the labor movement.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut labor, as well as the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students, etc. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut—history
Document Types:
Notes.; Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Publications.; Administrative records.; Photographs.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The papers were transferred from the University of Connecticut Labor Education Center to the University Libraries Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division (now Archives & Special Collections) in 1979.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Labor Union Materials, undated, 1936-1972
  - Automation, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Bishop, Merlin D.—personal, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1944-1962 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Drama, undated, 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union—Handbook of trade Union Methods, 1937 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Labor Education, undated, 1936-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Labor History, undated, 1936, 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Labor Leaders, undated, 1940, 1950 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Labor and Nation, v. III #4, 1947 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - “Labor Problems” and labor relations and the War, 1939-1948 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Lewis, John L., undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Parliamentary procedures
    - The ABC of Parliamentary Law, 1936, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - General publications, undated, 1922-1963 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - "How to conduct a Union meeting", undated, 1934-1942 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Parliamentary law, undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Union publications, undated, 1953 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - Union rules of order, 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, undated, 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Reuther, Walter, undated, 1969 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1945 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Seidman, Joel (Sit Down), 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Sinclair, Upton (The Flivver King, undated (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Staff leadership school, undated, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Textile Union workshop: “How can a Union build its program?”, 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Textile Workers Union of America—Rules for Union Meetings, 1950 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1962, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Time Study
    - AFL-CIO, 1958-1964 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - AFL-CIO publications, 1957-1962 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - Donald Beecher, undated (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - Merlin Bishop, undated (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - Bertram Gottlieb, undated, 1957, 1959 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Robert Kanter, 1956 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - William O. Kuhl, undated (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - News clippings and articles, 1944-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - Publications, 1948-1952 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - United Automobile Workers—CIO, undated (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Union contracts, 1948-1949 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - United Automobile Workers
    - History, 1946-1963 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - Publications, 1946-1963 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - Region 6 UAW summer school, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
    - The Workers in the automobile industry, undated (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - Walter and May Reuther Family Education Center, 1976 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Wallace, Henry A. (Sixty Million Jobs), 1945 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
  - Wilkie, Wendell L. (One World), 1943 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
  - Workers Education
    - American Federation of Teachers, Local 189, 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
    - Labor history, undated (Box 3:, Folder 47)
    - Methods, 1937-1939 (Box 3:, Folder 48)
    - Publications, 1955 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - Union songs, undated (Box 3:, Folder 50)
  - “WPA Cash backs CIO”—articles and comments, 1937 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
- Series II: University of Connecticut, undated, 1950-1975
  - Babbidge, Homer D., 1962-1970 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
  - Babbidge, Homer D.—speeches, 1963-1969 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - Bishop, Merlin D., undated, 1963 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - Bishop, Merlin D.—correspondence, 1950-1970 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - Committee on Religion at UConn, report of, 1965 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
  - Dave, Roger—The UConn Story, of The Miracle at Storrs Health Center, 1953 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
    - College of Veterinary Medicine for New England New Jersey, A feasibility study, 1973 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
    - Commission for Higher Education
      - Meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
      - Reports, undated, 1971 (Box 4:, Folder 60)
      - Report on Health Center, 1972 (Box 4:, Folder 61)
      - “Compendium of Materials assembled...”, 1972 (Box 4:, Folder 62)
    - Construction history, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 63)
  - Health Center
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 64)
    - Legislature, 1955-1957 (Box 4:, Folder 65)
    - Medical School Facilities Planning Consideration, 1961 (Box 4:, Folder 66)
    - Memoranda and notes, 1955-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 67)
    - Minutes (BOT) excerpts, 1961 (Box 5:, Folder 68)
    - News clippings, 1954-1961 (Box 5:, Folder 69)
    - Reports, 1954-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - Jorgensen, Albert N., 1954-1967 (Box 5:, Folder 71)
  - Labor Education Center
    - “Connecticut Labor management contract analysis”, 1969 (Box 5:, Folder 72)
    - Publications, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 73)
    - Responses to Hansen Report and Bishop Committee Report, 1970-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
  - Labor Education Center Study Committee
    - Correspondence, 1964-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 75)
    - Hansen Report, 1966 (Box 5:, Folder 76)
    - Institute of Public Service, 1967-1970 (Box 5:, Folder 77)
    - Notes, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 78)
    - Report to President Babbidge, 1964 (Box 5:, Folder 79)
    - Report on reconvening of Bishop Committee, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 80)
    - Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 81)
  - Land Grant Colleges, 1954, 1962 (Box 5:, Folder 82)
  - MacDonald Committee Report, 1954 (Box 5:, Folder 83)
  - McEvers, Hugh—UConn, Then and Now, 1962 (Box 5:, Folder 84)
  - News clippings, 1953-1967 (Box 5:, Folder 85)
  - Publications, 1951-1957 (Box 5:, Folder 86)
  - Salaries and tenure, 1972 (Box 5:, Folder 87)
  - “Senior questionnaire”, 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 88)
  - “Study of the problems confronting higher education in Connecticut”, 1957 (Box 6:, Folder 89)
  - Tuition—fees, 1962 (Box 6:, Folder 90)
  - Subseries A: Board of Trustees, 1951-1975
    - Minutes
      - 1951 (Box 7:, Folder 91)
      - 1952 January - June (Box 7:, Folder 92)
      - 1952 July - December (Box 7:, Folder 93)
      - 1953 (Box 7:, Folder 94)
      - 1954 (Box 7:, Folder 95)
      - 1955 (Box 7:, Folder 96)
      - 1956 (Box 7:, Folder 97)
      - 1957 (Box 7:, Folder 98)
      - 1958 (Box 7:, Folder 99)
      - 1959 (Box 8:, Folder 100)
      - 1960 (Box 8:, Folder 101)
      - 1961 (Box 8:, Folder 102)
      - 1962 (Box 8:, Folder 103)
      - 1963 (Box 8:, Folder 104)
      - 1964 (Box 9:, Folder 105)
      - 1966 (Box 9:, Folder 106)
      - 1967 (Box 9:, Folder 107)
      - 1968 (Box 9:, Folder 108)
      - 1969 (Box 10:, Folder 109)
      - 1970 (Box 10:, Folder 110)
      - 1971 (Box 10:, Folder 111)
      - 1972 January - April (Box 11:, Folder 112)
      - 1972 May - August (Box 11:, Folder 113)
      - 1972 September - December (Box 11:, Folder 114)
      - 1973 January - March (Box 11:, Folder 115)
      - 1973 April - August (Box 11:, Folder 116)
      - 1973 September - December (Box 11:, Folder 117)
      - 1974 January - April (Box 11:, Folder 118)
      - 1974 May - August (Box 11:, Folder 119)
      - 1974 September - December (Box 11:, Folder 120)
      - 1975 January - March (Box 11:, Folder 121)
  - Subseries B: Connecticut Commission on Higher Education, 1964-1973
    - Implementation of Public Act 194, 1972 (Box 12:, Folder 122)
    - Minutes
      - 1968 (Box 12:, Folder 123)
      - 1969 (Box 12:, Folder 124)
      - 1970 January - July (Box 12:, Folder 125)
      - 1970 September - December (Box 12:, Folder 126)
      - 1971 January - July (Box 12:, Folder 127)
      - 1971 September - December (Box 12:, Folder 128)
      - 1972 January - February (Box 12:, Folder 129)
      - 1972 March - May (Box 12:, Folder 130)
    - Preliminary draft of Master Plan for Higher Education in Connecticut, 1974-1979, 1973 (Box 12:, Folder 131)
    - General Assembly, An Act Establishing a State System of Higher Education, Public Act 330, 1965 (Box 13:, Folder 132)
    - General Assembly, Revised Education Statutes, 1971 (Box 13:, Folder 133)
    - Higher Education in Connecticut, Report of a Survey, 1964
      - Volume I—working papers (Box 13:, Folder 134)
      - Volume II—Summary, Conclusions, and Recommendations (Box 13:, Folder 135)
    - Higher Education Study Commission
      - “History” correspondence and notes, 1965, 1968 (Box 13:, Folder 136)
      - “History” General Assembly bills, undated, 1965 (Box 13:, Folder 137)
      - “History” news clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 13:, Folder 138)
      - “History” reference material, 1964-1965 (Box 13:, Folder 139)
      - Report to the Governor and the General Assembly, 1965 (Box 13:, Folder 140)
      - Statements, news clippings, 1965 (Box 13:, Folder 141)
  - Subseries C: Governor's Fact-Finding Commission on Education, undated, 1949-1975
    - Connecticut Report—Skeleton key, undated (Box 13:, Folder 142)
    - Education in Connecticut: A summary report to Chester Bowles, 1950 (Box 13:, Folder 143)
    - Fact-Finding Commission on Education
      - News clippings, articles, photographs, 1949-1951 (Box 13:, Folder 144)
      - Do Citizens and Education Mix?, undated (Box 13:, Folder 145)
      - “How the Youth Education Committee Worked”, undated (Box 13:, Folder 146)
    - Liaison Committee
      - Clippings, undated, 1954 (Box 14:, Folder 147)
      - “The Future of Higher Education in Connecticut”, 1956 (Box 14:, Folder 148)
    - Reference Material
      - Equity of Access: Continuing Education and the Part-Time Student, 1975 (Box 14:, Folder 149)
      - Institutional Aid, 1972 (Box 14:, Folder 150)
      - More Effective Use of Resources, 1972 (Box 14:, Folder 151)
      - Reform on Campus, 1972 (Box 14:, Folder 152)
    - Simpson, Alfred D., Financing of Public Education in Connecticut, undated (Box 14:, Folder 153)
- Series III: Dorothy H. Bishop, undated, 1924-1947
  - Affiliated Schools for Workers, Inc., I Am a Woman Worker, 1936 (Box 15:, Folder 154)
  - American Labor Education Service—Alfred Lewis, What your Union Means, 1941 (Box 15:, Folder 155)
  - Bibliography and speakers, undated (Box 15:, Folder 156)
  - Brookwood College List, undated, 1936 (Box 15:, Folder 157)
  - Caldwell, Erksine, You have seen their faces, 1937 (Box 15:, Folder 158)
  - Drama, 1936-1937 (Box 15:, Folder 159)
  - Economics, undated, 1926 (Box 15:, Folder 160)
  - Family Welfare Association of America, Case Work in Public Relief, 1935-1937 (Box 15:, Folder 161)
  - Federal Emergency Relief Administration, "Report on Camps for Unemployed Women, 1934, 1935,", 1936 (Box 15:, Folder 162)
  - Federal labor Relations Art of 1947 (Box 15:, Folder 163)
  - Household Employment
    - Correspondence, 1930-1942 (Box 15:, Folder 164)
    - Hubbard, Dorothy L., notebook, 1926-1930 (Box 15:, Folder 165)
    - Hurst, Marion, Household Employees Handbook, 1939 (Box 15:, Folder 166)
    - Industrial Girls Club, 1930-1933 (Box 16:, Folder 167)
    - News clippings and articles, 1939-1941 (Box 16:, Folder 168)
    - Poetry and writings, undated, 1934 (Box 16:, Folder 169)
    - Reports, 1930-1938 (Box 16:, Folder 170)
    - Unionization, undated (Box 16:, Folder 171)
    - Women's Trade Union League, undated (Box 16:, Folder 172)
    - YWCA questionnaires, undated (Box 16:, Folder 173)
  - “Industrial Work Histories, Olco.”, 1929 (Box 16:, Folder 174)
  - Injunctions, 1930 (Box 16:, Folder 175)
  - International Ladies Garment Workers Union—Handbook of Trade Union Methods, 1937 (Box 16:, Folder 176)
  - Labor History, 1927-1934 (Box 16:, Folder 177)
  - Labor journalism—Brookwood College, 1931-1932 (Box 16:, Folder 178)
  - Labor journalism—Brookwood College, 1935-1936 (Box 16:, Folder 179)
  - Labor problems—Labor movement today, 1929-1934 (Box 16:, Folder 180)
  - Notes on employment and pay rates, 1926-1932 (Box 16:, Folder 181)
  - Occupational grouping, 1932-1947 (Box 16:, Folder 182)
  - Philosophy, 1924 (Box 16:, Folder 183)
  - Pollak, Katherine H., Our Labor Movement Today, 1932 (Box 16:, Folder 184)
  - “Statistically Speaking”, undated (Box 16:, Folder 185)
  - Teaching methods, 1931-1937 (Box 17:, Folder 186)
  - Union songs, undated (Box 17:, Folder 187)
  - United Auto Workers—Proceedings of the Second Convention, 1936 (Box 17:, Folder 188)
  - Utah Workers Progress Administration Education Program, 1936-1937 (Box 17:, Folder 189)
  - Writings and literature, 1920, 1931 (Box 17:, Folder 190)
  - YWCA
    - Camp Gray material, 1933-1934 (Box 17:, Folder 191)
    - Report of Industrial staff, undated (Box 17:, Folder 192)
    - YWCA, undated (Box 17:, Folder 193)
    - “Young Women's Christian Association and Industry”, 1928 (Box 17:, Folder 194)